Osip Mandelʹshtam Papers, 1900s-1970s (bulk 1914-1937 ): Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
Osip Mandelʹshtam Papers
1900s-1970s
1914-1937
C0539
Princeton University. Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections Manuscripts Division One Washington Road Princeton, New Jersey 08544 USA
2.4 linear feet 6 boxes
Mandelʹshtam, Osip, 1891-1938.
Osip Mandelʹshtam was a Russian poet, novelist, essayist and critic. A member of the Guild of Poets, a radical faction of the acmeist movement in poetry, he criticized the literary conformity demanded by Russia’s new communist government. The collection consists of Russian-language works, correspondence, and printed matter of Mandelʹshtam. It contains holograph and typed manuscripts of his poems, reviews, articles, and essays, often in draft form representing different stages of his work, many of which are in the hand of his wife, Nadezhda, who acted as his amanuensis.
Osip Mandelʹshtam was a Russian poet, novelist, essayist and critic. A member of the Guild of Poets, a radical faction of the acmeist movement in poetry, he criticized the literary conformity demanded by Russia's new communist government. In 1918, he narrowly escpaed execution after destroying a stack of death warrants belonging to a government official. In 1934, Mandelʹshtam was arrested after reading an anti-Stalin poem to a group of friends, one of whom informed on him. He spent three years in exile. He obtained his release in 1937 with the help of Boris Pasternak and other artists who intervened on his behalf, but was rearrested in 1938. The date and place of his death are uncertain, but many biographers believe he died in 1938 in a prison camp near Vladivostok, Siberia.
Consists of Russian-language works, correspondence, and printed matter of Osip Emil'evich Mandelʹshtam. The collection contains holograph and typed manuscripts of his poems, reviews, articles, and essays, often in draft form representing different stages of his work, many of which are in the hand of his wife, Nadezhda, who acted as his amanuensis. Among the works are the following collections of poetry: Kamen, Tristia, Poems (1928), New Poems, and Voronezh Notebooks. Prose works include Fourth Prose, Journey to Armenia, Conversation About Dante, and The Egyptian Stamp. A copy of Kamen belonging to S. P. Kablukov and Poems (1928) inscribed to N. E. Shtempel are also in the collection. In addition, there are official documents; correspondence as well as notations by Nadezhda on Mandelʹshtam's political situation; letters from Mandelʹshtam to Nadezhda [Khazina]; and letters from Soviet poet Anna Akhmatova, a letter from Arthur Miller, and others, some of which contain references to the Writer's Union.
Abbreviations: OM = Osip Emil'evich Mandelʹshtam, NM = Nadezhda Iakovlevna Mandelʹshtam
Transliteration: Titles are cited in accordance with Library of Congress transliteration rules. In addition, Russian titles are cited in the poetry index, as well as on folders.
Poem numbering: To facilitate research, material for each poem found in manuscripts is identified by the number under which the poem is listed in the most complete edition of Osip Mandelʹshtam's Collected Works (the edition is hereafter referred to as the New York edition):
Sobranie sochinenii. Edited by Gleb Struve, Nikita Struve and Boris Filippov. New York: Inter-Language Literary Associates; Paris: YMCA-Press, 1964-1981.
vol. I (Poetry). Introductions by Clarence Brown and Gleb Struve. Second edition, revised and expanded, 1967.
vol. II (Prose). Introductions by Boris Filippov. 1966. Second edition, revised and expanded, 1971.
vol.III (Essays and Letters). Introductions by George Ivask, Nikita Struve and Boris Filippov, 1969.
vol. IV (Supplement Volume), 1981.
For poems, variants and fragments not found in the New York edition, the title/first line is followed by "no. ?".
Titles:
Prose: titles are cited as given in manuscripts, earlier manuscript descriptions, or published texts; if an item has a working title that was changed in final version, that title is cited in square brackets; if an item is incomplete, unpublished and unidentified, first line in square brackets is cited as title.
Poetry: untitled poems identified by first line; fragments of poems (drafts of individual stanzas, lines, etc.) not listed in the New York edition as variants under a separate number are cited by italicized title/first line in square brackets of listed poem/variant under a separate number they refer to.
Dates: Dates in the date column are cited as given in manuscripts and copies, and indicate the time when the item was written, not the time the copy was made.
Prose and letters: if no date is given in manuscript/copy, date written is, wherever possible, taken from earlier descriptions, the New York edition, or, in case of letters, sometimes deduced from contents; it is cited in square brackets.
Poetry: since in many cases different manuscripts and copies of the same poem give conflicting day/month references, the date in the date column is cited exactly as in this or that particular manuscript/copy. If no date is given, undated is entered in the date column. If only month and/or day is given, the year is deduced from other sources and cited in square brackets.
Manuscripts vs. Copies: Distinctions are made (always based on earlier descriptions - primarily I. Semenko's) between manuscripts in the hand of Nadezhda Mandelʹshtam (made from the author's drafts and revised by him, dictated by the author, etc.) and copies in her hand. Also, distinctions are made between NM's copies made in OM's lifetime and copies made after his death in 1938.
The collection has been foldered strictly in the order in which it was found. Most of the material had been previously processed and described. Many items were identified and grouped by Nadezhda Mandelʹshtam; part of the collection was organized by Nikolai Khardzhiev; much of the work on collating and describing poetry and prose manuscripts was done by Irina Semenko. The present inventory draws almost exclusively on these earlier descriptions. In several cases, however, no description was available, and attempts were made to organize certain items (without disturbing the original order of item envelopes) and identify them. Thus, Nadezhda Mandelʹshtam's correspondence (Box 3, Folders 102-104) has been itemized and chronologically arranged within the three envelopes in which it was originally placed. Some additional corrections (Boxes 1 & 3) have been made by Pavel Polian (Nerler) in December 1999.
Material for some items was frequently found in different parts of the collection, therefore, for prose, cross-reference has been made to relevant folders. Besides, for poetry and for prose, respective indexes to titles and first lines have been compiled. For letters, there are indexes to addressees and senders.
In accordance with the wishes of Nadezhda Mandelʹshtam, only photocopies (Box 7-11) of the papers are to be used by researchers in order to help preserve the originals, which may only be used with the permission of the Curator of Manuscripts.
Digital images of the papers are available online.
The Papers of Osip Mandelʹshtam (1891-1938) were entrusted by the poet's widow Nadezhda Mandelʹshtam to Prof. Nikita Struve to be taken out of the Soviet Union in two valises and temporarily kept in Paris until they could be given to Prof. Clarence Brown of Princeton University. In 1976 Prof. Elliott Mossman of the University of Pennsylvania, acting as an agent for Princeton University, assisted by securing the papers from Struve, who had taken them to Paris. While Nadezhda Mandelʹshtam proposed either giving the papers to Princeton University or Clarence Brown personally, Professor Brown did not wish to own them personally and therefore had University counsel Thomas H. Wright prepare a deed of gift for Nadezhda Mandelʹshtam's signature.
Clarence Brown Papers (C1571)
Mandelʹshtam, Nadezhda, 1899-1980.; Soi︠u︡z pisateleĭ SSSR.; Literature and state -- Soviet Union -- 20th century.; Russian poetry -- 20th century.; Russian prose literature -- 20th century.; Soviet Union -- Intellectual life -- 1917-1970.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts.; Poets, Russian -- 20th century.; European literature; Russia
- Stikhotvoreniia: book (Moscow: Gosudarstvennoe izdatel'stvo, 1928), 1937 March 1; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  Inscribed to "Natasha" [Shtempel'] in hand of OM -- V[oronezh], 1937 March 1; some corrections marked V[oronezh] [19]36 and [19]37 in hand of OM (black ink), notes and later additions to poems in hand of NM (pencil)
- Kamen', undated; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  Book (Petrograd: Giperborei, 1915); inscribed by OM to Sergei Platonovich Kablukov. 1915 December 2 additional poems written in book and on inserted sheets, all in hand of S. P. Kablukov unless otherwise noted; most poems dated (1915) (1915 December 2)
  1. Moskva (V raznogolositse devicheskogo khora...), no. 84 -- 2. Kto znaet? Mozhet byt' ne khvatit mne svechi..., variant (Kogda sgustilsia mrak nad venchikom svechi...) -- 3. Na rozval'niakh, ulozhennykh solomoi..., no. 85 -- 4. Ia poteriala nezhnuiu kameiiu..., no. 87 -- 5. Solominka (Kogda, solominka, ne spish v ogromnoi spalne...), no. 86 -- 6. Sobiralis' elliny voinoi..., no. 70 -- 7. Tomu svidetel'stvo --iazychskii senat..., no. 94 -- 8. Zolotistogo meda struia iz butylki tekla..., no. 92 -- 9. Iudeiam (A. V. Kartashevu) (Sredi sviashchennikov levitom molodym...), no. 100 -- 10. Kogda oktiabr'skii nam gotovil vremenshchik..., no. 192: newspaper clipping -- 11. Notre Dame ( Gde rimskii sudiia sudil chuzhoi narod...), no. 39: printed page from a different book -- 12. [Otryvok] ("...No v starom Kelne tozhe est' sobor..."), no. ? -- 13. [Otryvok] ("Kakaia veshchaia Kassandra..."), no. 180 -- 14. O, etot vozdukh smutnyi, p'ianyi..., no. 107 -- 15. Petropol': stanza I ("Mne kholodno. Prozrachnaia vesna...") no. 88, stanza II omitted in later publications, stanza III ("V Petropole prozrachnom my umrem...) no. 89 -- 16. Kak etikh pokryval i etogo ubora..., no. 82 -- 17. S veselym rhzaniem pasutsia tabuny..., no. 80 -- 18. Miru (oda), Zverinets) (Otverzhennoe slovo "mir"...), no. 83 (slightly different version) -- 19. Madrigal (Kniagine Andronnikovoi) (Doch Andronika Komnena...), no. 512 -- 20. Unichtozhaet plamen'..., no. 73 -- 21. Imiabozhie (I ponyne na Afone...), no. 75 -- 22. Evkharistiia (Vot daronositsa, kak solntse zolotoe...), no. 117 -- 23. O svobode nebyvaloi..., no. 77 -- 24. Na pogrebenie materi (Eta noch nepopravima...), no. 91 -- 25. Moi tikhii son, moi son ezheminutnyi..., no. 145: handwritten on p.7 -- 26. Istonchaetsia tonkii tlen..., no. 146 -- 27. Net, ne podniat' volshebnogo fregata..., variant (Mne gashisha bezumnogo ne nado..., no. ? -- 28. Zdes' otvratitel'nye zhaby..., no. 146 -- 29. V moroznom vozdukhe rastaial legkii dym..., no. 183: handwritten on p.14 -- 30. Temnykh uz zemnogo zatocheniia..., no. 158 -- 31. Iz omuta zlogo i viazkogo..., no. 17 -- 32. Kogda pokazyvaiut vosem'..., no. 160 -- 33. Neu(m?)olimye slova..., no. 182 -- 34. V lazuri mesiats novyi..., no. 155: handwritten on p.20 -- 35. V samom sebe, kak zmei taias'..., no. 162 -- 36. Kak ten' vnezapnykh oblakov..., no. 16 -- 37. Kogda udar s udarami vstrechaetsia..., no. 12 -- 38. Na perlamutrovyi chelnok..., no. 10: handwritten on p.24 -- 39. Dusha ustala ot usilii..., no. 15: handwritten on p.27 -- 40. Ot legkoi zhizni my soshli s uma..., no. 43 -- 41. Sport (Rumianyi shkiper brosil miach tiazhelyi...), no. 166: handwritten on p.60-61 -- 42. Zasnula chern', ziiaet propast' arkoi..., no. 163: handwritten on p.62 -- 43. Avtoportret (V podniat'i golovy krylatoi...), no. 164: handwritten on p.64 -- 44. Pust' imena tsvetushchikh gorodov..., no. 66 -- 45. Priroda tot zhe Rim..., no. 65: variants -- 46. Nemetskaia kaska --sviashchennyi trofei..., no. 179: handwritten on p.75 -- 47. Kak ovtsy zhalkoiu tolpoi..., no. 178: handwritten on p.78 -- 48. Liuter v Vormse (Zdes' ia stoiu -- ia ne mogu inache...), no. 42: handwritten on p.79 -- 49. Variant, appended to Abbat (no. 74): handwritten on p. 79 -- 50. Ot vtornika i do subboty..., no. 76 -- 51. Amerikanka (Amerikanka v dvadtsat' let...), no. 52 -- 52. Variant of Abbat, (no. 74) -- 53. Imperatorskii Visson, no. 199: handwritten on p.85 -- 54. Kakoi prozrachnyi blesk..., poem by S. P. Kablukov -- 55. Rus', ne tebia dukh mesti lichnoi..., poem by Viacheslav Ivanov -- 56. [ Blagovolni...]; (poem by S. P. Kablukov?) -- 57. Kogda mozaik niknut travy..., no. 152 -- 58. Negodovan'e starcheskoi kifary..., no. 184 -- 59. Egiptianin (Ia izbezhal surovoi peni...), no. 171: printed page from a different book -- 60. Egiptianin (Ia vystroil sebe blagopoluchia dom...), no. 172 -- 61. Pust' v dushnoi komnate, gde klochia seroi vaty..., no. 173 -- 62. "My boimsia, my ne smeem...": translation of Phèdre by Jean Racine, closing fragment, no. 82 (first version)
- Drafts of poems; draft of translation (fragments) (undated), 1 folder (Folder 3)
  1. Kak rastet khlebov opara..., no. 130: draft of poem in hand of OM -- 2. Ia poteriala nezhnuiu kameiu..., no. 87: poem typewritten on obverse of item 1, pencil sketches in margins -- 3. [ Vazha Pshavela] Gogotur i Apshina ( Govoriat, iz Bloia Apshina...), no. 466: translation of poem by that author (draft fragment), in hand of OM, editorial corrections in hand of NM -- 4. [Vazha Pshavela], no. 466: fragment of translation draft, front page in hand of NM, inside pages in hand of OM, title on cover in hand of N. Khardzhiev
- Poem manuscripts; translation draft (1911 August 22-1916 January 11), undated; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  1. Dozhdik laskovyi, melkii i tonkii..., no. 504: two author's manuscripts, corrections in hand of OM, both dated -- 2. Oda voiuiushchim derzhavam (alt. title in pencil Mir), no. ?: author's manuscript of poem -- 3. I derzkii probezhal po riadam vostorg...: translation draft of play by Jules Romain, fragment, in hand of OM
- Printed article, article drafts, letter (1914 November 3-1915), undated; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  1. "Petr Chaadaev": printed journal article; source: Apollon (Sep. 1915; no. 6-7), pp.57-62 -- 2. "Petr Chaadaev": fragments of author's draftNote: (On reverse of sheet 3) -- 3. Letter from Headmaster of Teneshev School to E. V. Mandelstam (OM's father)
- ["Retsenziia na knigu I. Erenburga"]: review of book by Il'ia Ehrenburg, fragment of author's draft, title on cover in hand of N. Khardzhiev, undated; 1 folder (Folder 6)
- "Opravdanie sobornoi idei": outline of artlicle, in hand of OM, title on cover in hand of N. Khardzhiev, undated; 1 folder (Folder 7)
- ["Otryvok iz stat'i"]: fragment of lost article, draft in hand of OM, title on cover in hand of N. Khardzhiev, undated; 1 folder (Folder 8)
- "O momente ‘obshcheniia’ v poeticheskom tvorchestve": article, published in 1913 as "O sobesednike," fragments of final typescript (pp. 1-2, 5-6), undated; 1 folder (Folder 9)
- "K vykhodu "Al'manakha muz": article, complete author's draft, title on first cover in hand of N. Khardzhiev, on second in hand of NM, 1916; 1 folder (Folder 10)
- Fragments of article draft, letter (1915-1918), undated; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  1. "Skriabin i khristianstvo": article, published as Pushkin i Skriabin, fragments of author's manuscript (text of complete article lost), title on cover in hand of N. Khardzhiev on obverse of last sheet -- 2. Letter from E. E. Mandelʹshtam (OM's brother) to Headqurters of Chief of Staff
- ["Lui Pergo"]: review of book on animals by Louis Pergaud, complete author's draft, 1930s; 1 folder (Folder 12)
- Fragments of article draft; poems (1914-1926), undated; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  1. "Kiev": essay, fragments of draft, one sheet in hand of OM, two sheets in hand of NM; for NM's copy of printed text see B2 F5, 1926 on reverse of sheets: typescripts of 5 poems -- 2. Chistil'shchik: no. 408 -- 3. Avtomobilishche, fragment, no. 409 -- 4. Kooperativ, no. 413 -- 5. Mukha, fragment, no.414 -- 6. Zverinets (Otverzhennoe slovo "Mir"...), stanzas 5 and 6, no. 83
- "Berezil'": essay, fragments of copy in hand of NM published, 1926; 1 folder (Folder 14)
- "Vozvrashchenie": essay/memoir, unfinished; complete copy in hand of NM, undated; 1 folder (Folder 15)
- "Ogiust Barb'e": article on Auguste Barbier, fragment ofcopy in hand of Nm published, 1923; 1 folder (Folder 16)
- OM's correspondence with publisher (ZIF) and Federation of Soviet Writers, 1928-1932; 1 folder (Folder 17)
  Typewritten transcript of letters from and to OM regarding publishing agreements and royalties for translations; also transcripts of OM's statements and letters concerning accusations of plagiarism in his copies translation of Eulenspiegel Legend
- "Shpigun": film review, complete original typescript, 1929; 1 folder (Folder 18)
- "Veer gertsogini": article on literary criticism, complete original typescript, notes in hand of NM, 1926; 1 folder (Folder 19)
- "Krovavaia misteriia 9-go ianvaria": article, first two sheets of typescript; for fragments of copy in hand of E. Ia. Khazin see Box 2, Folder 12, 1922; 1 folder (Folder 20)
- "Men'sheviki v Gruzii": essay/memoir, typedmanuscript, corrections and comments on margins in hand of NM, 1923; 1 folder (Folder 21)
- "Sukharevka", 1923; 1 folder (Folder 22)
  Essay, fragments of author's manuscript, first paragraph of first page in hand of NM, original typescript, correctionsin hand of NM, a note in red ink on top of first page: "Piece not suitable for Izvestiia due to lack of social critique. Will do for Vecherka [Vecherniaia Moskva]."
- "Kukla s millionami": film review, complete original typescript, also later copy of opening fragment in hand of NM, 1926; 1 folder (Folder 23)
- "Kholodnoe leto": essay, complete typescript, also carbon copy of last page, 1923; 1 folder (Folder 24)
- ["Otryvki o Mikhoelse"]: article, unfinished, fragments of author's draft; for NM's copy of printed text see Box 2, Folder 6, 1926; 1 folder (Folder 25)
- "O poetakh: 2. Kto zhe oni takie?", 1923; 1 folder (Folder 26)
  Magazine article, first published as "Armiia poetov," original typed manuscript, page 4 missing, corrections in hand of NM; for NM's copy of part 1 see Box 2, Folder 12
- "Stat'ia o perevodakh": article on translations, fragment of original typescript, title and date on cover and sheet in hand of NM, circa 1931; 1 folder (Folder 27)
- "Stat'ia o Serafimoviche", 1926; 1 folder (Folder 28)
  Review of a book by Aleksandr Serafimovich, author's draft, five sheets of transcript in hand of NM, first page and carbon copy of typed transcript
- Drafts of novella, translation fragments (1927-1928), undated; 1 folder (Folder 29)
  1. Egipetskaia marka: novella, OM's largest work of fictional prose, collated fragments of author's draft manuscript, also typed transcripts with handwritten drafts on obverse, some sheets withdrawings and sketches in margins; last four pages written on obverse of -- 2. Translation of Eulenspiegel Legend by Charles de Coster: fragments of typescript
- Early translations (1910-1924), undated; 1 folder (Folder 30)
  1. Fragment of translation: untitled, unidentified, final manuscript in hand of OM -- 2. Pervaia vigiliia: fragment of translation, source [ The Golden?] by T. A. Goffmann, final manuscript with corrections in hand of OM
- 1. prose about "Finlandiia": fragments of author's draft (text not included in final version), one sheet with drawings in margins on obverse (1924). 2. Egipetskaia marka: fragment in hand of OM (undated), 1 folder (Folder 31)
- Fragments of OM's letters to authorities regarding his physical condition and living situation in Voronezh, 1926-1937; 1 folder (Folder 32)
  Three sheets in NM's hand (copies of OM's manuscripts or dictated by him)
- Two letters on one sheet (1931), undated; 1 folder (Folder 33)
  1. Letter from OM to NM: handwritten, on obverse of page 2 -- 2. Letter from MN to OM: reply to above letter both
- Two letters from NM to OM: fragments, handwritten, 1919; 1 folder (Folder 34)
- OM's note to NM: 1 sheet in OM's hand, undated; 1 folder (Folder 35)
- Letter from A. A. Akhmatova to NM: handwritten, 1940s; 1 folder (Folder 36)
- Telegram from OM and E. E. Mandelʹshtam (OM's brother) to NM, regarding OM's transfer to sanitarium, 1920s; 1 folder (Folder 37)
- Letter from B. Buchshtab to NM: one typed sheet regarding OM's manuscripts in state and private archives, signature illegible, 1968 January 20; 1 folder (Folder 38)
- Postcard from A. A. Akhmatova to NM: addressed to NM in Tashkent, 1945 August; 1 folder (Folder 39)
- Letter from OM to S. Z. Fedorchenko: typewritten copy of original letter, original kept in Central Literary Archives (TsGALI) in Moscow, 1924 July 9; 1 folder (Folder 40)
- Letter from V. Merkulov to I. Ehrenburg, 1952; 1 folder (Folder 41)
  :Typewritten, contains typescript of OM's poem: Rekviem (na smert' Andreiia Belogo) (10 ianvaria 1934) ( Menia presleduiut dve-tri sluchainykh frazy...), no. 289 letter
- Transcript of OM's oral comments: one sheet in hand of NM, comments on Othello, Pasternak and Goethe, undated; 1 folder (Folder 42)
- Letter from "Natasha" [Shtempel'] to NM: handwritten, regarding OM's manuscripts and Voronezh poems, 1967; 1 folder (Folder 43)
- Notebook: five sheets in OM's hand, apparently notes for radioplay on Goethe ( Iunost' Gete), 1935; 1 folder (Folder 44)
- Molodost' Gete, 1935; 1 folder (Folder 45)
  Radioplay on Goethe's youth, original typescript, some pages missing, corrections in hand of NM, published in New York edition as Iunost' Gete
- Molodost' Gete: radioplay on Goethe's youth, fragments of draft, 1935; 1 folder (Folder 46)
- Article manuscript and drafts; telegram (1923-1928), undated; 1 folder (Folder 47)
  1. "Zametki o Shen'e": article on André Chenier, fragments of draft, several sheets of final manuscript, all in hand of NM first published, 1928, (one draft sheet written on obverse of 2) -- 2. Telegram from " Otets" (OM's father) to Khazim Mandelʹshtam
- Chetvertaia proza: two copies of manuscript, both in hand of NM, ten sheets each, one copy apparently older (made in OM's lifetime?), undated; 1 folder (Folder 48)
- Notebook in NM's hand: 10 handwritten sheets, one typed (1935), undated; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  1. Kama ( Kak na Kame-reke glazu temno, kogda...): poem (variant), no. 309 -- 2. Mir nachinalsia strashen i velik: poem, no. 516 corrections in OM's hand -- 3. Chernozem ( Pereuvazhena, perecherna, vsia v khole...), no. 299 -- 4. Ia zhivu na vazhnykh ogorodakh..., no. 304 -- 5. Ia smotrel, otdaliaias', na khvoinyi vostok..., no. 310 -- 6. [Notes on Chekhov's Diadia Vania]: article draft -- 7. Kanatella ( Umoliaiu, Kanatella...), no. 557, typewritten
- "Khardzhievskie oblozhki" ("Khardzhiev's covers": title on original folder): manuscripts kept and organized by N. I. Khardzhiev (1967-1969), undated; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  1. "Al'bom 1935": soft folder with title in hand of N. I. Khardzhiev, contains covers for individual poem manuscripts, some covers made by Khardzhiev, some by NM, contents missing -- 2. "Sosnovaia roshchitsa. Zadonsk": NM's biographical note on two poems written in Zadonsk ( Plastinkoi tonen'koi zhilleta... (no. 297) and Sosnovoi roshchitsy zakon... no. 333))
- "Khardzhievskie oblozhki" (undated), 1 folder (Folder 3)
  1-30. "Armeniia": folder with thirty covers for individual poem manuscripts, most in hand N. Khardzhiev, some in hand of NM, contents missing -- 31. "Put' v Armeniiu": essay/memoir, transcript of author's draft, handwritten, made by D. Borisov, note in red pencil on cover by I. Semenko indicates numerous errors in transcript
- "Literaturnaia Moskva", undated; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  Essay, handwritten copy of printed text, pages 1-4 in hand of E. Ia. Khazin (NM's brother), p.5 in hand of NM, on p.6 "A. Blok": article, fragment of handwritten copy in hand of E. Khazin (crossed out)